<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <chapter n="1">Chapter 1: <chapterTitle>The Arrival at Marseilles</chapterTitle></chapter>
    In the port of <place>Marseilles, France</place>, an eager crowd watches as a ship called the <ship>Pharaon</ship> pulls into dock. The ship’s owner, <character name="Morrel">Monsieur Morrel</character>, is greeted with sad news: the ship’s captain has died at sea. The nineteen-year-old first mate, <character name="Dantès">Edmond Dantès</character>, reassures <character>Morrel</character> that despite the loss of the captain, the trip went smoothly and all the cargo arrived safely. <character name="Morrel">Morrel</character> is impressed with the young man’s performance as temporary captain.
    <!--aw: I used <character name=""> so that if I were marking up the entire list of summaries or the entire book I could search for specific people-->
    <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character>, the ship’s supercargo, who is responsible for all financial matters, attempts to undermine <character name="Morrel">Morrel’s</character> good opinion of <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character>. <character name="Morrel">Morrel</character> boards the ship and <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character> tells him that <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> forced the ship to stop at the <place>Isle of Elba</place>, which cost them precious time. When <character name="Morrel">Morrel</character> confronts <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> with this accusation, <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> explains that he stopped the ship at <place>Elba</place> in order to carry out his captain’s dying request: to deliver a package to an exiled grand-marshal, <character name="Bertrand">Maréchal Bertrand</character>. He says that while he was on the island he spoke with <character name="Napoleon">Napoleon</character>, the deposed emperor of <place>France</place>.
    With this matter cleared up, <character name="Morrel">Morrel</character> asks <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> for his opinion of <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character>. <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> answers honestly, explaining that he has a personal dislike for <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character> but that <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character> does his work very well. <character name="Morrel">Morrel</character> approves of <character name="Dantès">Dantès’s</character> behavior at <place>Elba</place>, of his honest assessment of an enemy, and of his character in general. <character name="Morrel">Morrel</character> declares that after he consults with his partner, <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> will be named the new captain of the <ship>Pharaon</ship>, despite his young age. <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> is ecstatic, while <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character> is beside himself with envy.
    
    <chapter n="2">Chapter 2: <chapterTitle>Father and Son</chapterTitle></chapter>
    Leaving the docks, <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> goes straight to see his father. He is shocked by the old man’s physical deterioration and soon discovers its cause: his father has been starving for the past few months. Though <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> left his father with <num>200</num> francs, the tailor <character name="Caderousse">Caderousse</character> demanded that the <character name="L.Dantès">elder Dantès</character> pay him a debt that his son owed, which left the old man with only <num>sixty</num> francs on which to live. <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> tells his father the good news of his promotion and hands him a modest pile of gold, telling him to buy himself all the provisions he needs.
    
    <character name="Caderousse">Caderousse</character> then enters the small room to welcome <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> home. <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> receives <character name="Caderousse">Caderousse</character> politely, telling himself <quote>“he is a neighbour who has done us a service . . . so he’s welcome.”</quote> <character name="Caderousse">Caderousse</character> has already heard the news of <character name="Dantès">Dantès’s</character> promotion and congratulates him. <character name="Caderousse">Caderousse</character> then leaves the father and son and goes downstairs, where <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character> is waiting for him. The two men discuss their dislike for <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> and accuse him of being arrogant. <character name="Caderousse">Caderousse</character> reveals that <character name="Dantès">Dantès’s</character> good luck might be about to change: the woman he loves, <character name="Mercédès">Mercédès</character>, has been seen in the company of another man. <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character> and <character name="Caderousse">Caderousse</character>, hoping for the worst, decide to wait by the road near <character name="Mercédès">Mercédès’s</character> house, in order to determine whether <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> has really been jilted.
    
    <chapter n="3">Chapter 3: <chapterTitle>The Catalans</chapterTitle></chapter>
    As expected, <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> next goes to visit <character name="Mercédès">Mercédès</character>, a beautiful girl who belongs to the <ethnicGroup>Spanish community of Catalans.</ethnicGroup> He finds <character name="Mercédès">Mercédès</character> in the company of <character name="Mondego">Fernand Mondego</character>, her lovestruck cousin, who has been trying for years to make her his wife. <character name="Mercédès">Mercédès</character> welcomes <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> with a passionate embrace, and <charcter name="Mondego">Fernand</charcter> stalks off, enraged. <character name="Mondego">Fernand</character> passes <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character> and <character name="Caderousse">Caderousse</character> drinking wine by the side of the road, and they call him over. As the three men drink together, <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character> and <character name="Caderousse">Caderousse</character> try to whip <character name="Mondego">Fernand</character> up into a frenzy of envy and anger much like their own. <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> and <character name="Mercédès">Mercédès</character> appear, blissfully oblivious to the malice directed toward them. The couple tells <character name="Mondego">Fernand</character>, <character name="Caderousse">Caderousse</character>, and <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character> that they plan to be married the next day because <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> must travel to <place>Paris </place>to fulfill the last commission of his dead captain. Though <character name="Dantès">Dantès </character>does not state explicitly why he is going to <place>Paris</place>, <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character> suspects <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> is delivering a letter that has been entrusted to him by <character name="Napoleon">Napoleon</character> to Bonapartist plotters—supporters of <character name="Napoleon">Napoleon</character> who are helping him plan to overthrow the French government. The allusion to the letter sparks an evil idea in <character name="Danglars">Danglars’s</character> mind.
    
    <chapter n="4">Chapter 4: <chapterTitle>The Plotters</chapterTitle></chapter>
    <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character> and <character name="Mondego">Fernand</character> plot <character name="Dantès">Dantès’s</character> downfall as <character name="Caderousse">Caderousse</character> descends deep into intoxication. <character name="Mondego">Fernand</character> is unwilling to kill <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character>, since <character name="Mercédès">Mercédès</character> has promised to commit <motif>suicide</motif> should <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> die. <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character> suggests that they should have him imprisoned instead. <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character> drafts a letter informing the public prosecutor that <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> is bearing a letter from <character name="Napoleon">Napoleon</character> to the Bonapartist Committee in <location>Paris</location>. <character name="Caderousse">Caderousse</character> protests against this defamation of <character name="Dantès">Dantès’s</character> character, so <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character> makes a show of tossing the letter into a corner, telling <character name="Caderousse">Caderousse</character> that he is merely jesting. <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character> then leads <character name="Caderousse">Caderousse</character> away, and <character name="Mondego">Fernand</character>, as expected, retrieves the letter and plans to mail it.
    
    <chapter n="5">Chapter 5: <chapterTitle>The Betrothal Feast</chapterTitle></chapter>
    In the middle of <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> and <character name="Mercédès">Mercédès’s</character> betrothal feast, royal guards burst in and arrest <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character>. Everyone is confused, especially <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character>, who has done nothing wrong, as far as he knows. <character name="Danglars">Danglars</character> offers to take over duties as captain of the <ship>Pharaon</ship> until <character name="Dantès">Dantès</character> is released, and<character name="Morrel"> Morrel</character> gratefully accepts this offer.
</xml>
